Contact

integration1857@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ madhukarkumar1 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Analytics
Predictive Modeling
Predictive Analytics

Honors-Awards

Management Level 2 Award
Management Level 1 Award
Business Impact Award
MCM Scholarship
Rajiv Gandhi Memorial scholarship

Madhukar Kumar

Chief Analytics Officer | Al Evangelist | Speaker | Blogger | Educator | Marathoner | Triathlete | Sky Diver | MLESM
Gurgaon

Summary

Madhukar Kumar is Chief Analytics officer & Al Evangelist with 14+ years of expertise in data sciences, predictive analytics, Al, Machine learning, deep learning and consulting across a multitude of both global clients and verticals.

Madhukar has been conferred "Lifetime distinguished membership" of MLESM (Leader excellence at Harvard Square, based out of Massachusetts, US.

Madhukar was chosen as "Al Leader of the year" in IBAE 2019 Awards, Organized by GISR Foundation and The American college of Dubai. The felicitation ceremony was held in Park Regis Kris kin hotel, Dubai on 31st Oct,2019.

Madhukar's work on image analytics is well received in the industry. "The Drone image Analytics" solution was judged as one of the Top 50 applications of AI and was awarded Nasscom AI game changer 2018 award. Also, It won "Stevie Gold award-2018" under "Best product/service of the year" category.

Madhukar was rated as one of the Top 4 Data scientists from India by an Australian Advisory firm(Swami Associates) for significant contribution in science & Technology for Australian firms in 2015.

Madhukar is an avid blogger and regularly writes on Linkedin on various data science topics, He has started #datasciencewithmadhukar on Linkedin to share his experiences and thoughts on AI & data science. It crossed 350k+ views in the 2 months.

Madhukar is a well known speaker and speaks at various AI & Data science conferences.

Madhukar is also interested in Academics and teach data science @ various universities and spends considerable amount of time nurturing future data scientists across the globe.

Madhukar is a passionate athlete and has completed 1 Full marathon(42k), 5 half marathons(21k), 1 Olympic triathlon (1.5k swimming, 40k cycling, 10k running), 2 Cyclothons (70k & 130k), Sky diving & Scuba diving.

Experience

Shine.com
Chief Analytics Officer
June 2019 - Present (1 year 3 months)
Gurgaon, India

Leaders Excellence at Harvard Square
Lifetime Distinguished MLESM- Member of Leaders Excellence at
Harvard Square
March 2016 - Present (4 years 6 months)
Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA

Leaders Excellence is an exclusive online network at Harvard Square for midand upper-level management who want to grow as leaders and ascend to the next level of their professional career.

The goal is to empower driven professionals to cultivate a robust network of fellow leaders, one that facilitates long-lasting and beneficial business relationships. It's a holistic approach to developing stronger, more capable leaders who can lead successful organizations and contribute to a stronger global economy.

Leaders Excellence is supported by some of the world's most esteemed executives and professors from such prestigious universities like Yale, MIT, and Stanford. To preserve the integrity and exclusivity of our network, membership is offered on an invitation- or qualification-only basis.

Experfy

Blogger || Big Data || Machine learning || Advanced Analytics - Expert October 2015 - Present (4 years 11 months)

Harvard Innovation Launch Lab, Boston, US

WNS Global Services Chief Data Scientist February 2017 - June 2019 (2 years 5 months) Gurgaon, India

- 1. Developed an in-house image analytics product ÏMAGN" for insurance
- a) Received "NASSCOM AI Game Changer award 2018" and it was adjudged as one of the top 50 applications of AI
- b) Received "Stevie Gold Award 2018" under "Best product/service of the year" category

Great Learning
Guest Faculty - Data Science
July 2017 - January 2019 (1 year 7 months)
Gurgaon, India

UpGrad.com Director - Data Science May 2016 - December 2016 (8 months) Mumbai Area, India

SG Analytics
Principal Data Scientist & Delivery Head - Data Analytics

August 2015 - May 2016 (10 months)

Pune Area, India

WNS Global Services (P) Ltd

5 years 7 months

Principal Data Scientist & Head of Advanced Analytics Pilot Projects January 2015 - August 2015 (8 months)

Gurgaon

- Added 1st Banking logo for WNS in Australia beating 4 Analytics companies
- Lead a team of Data Scientists to deliver High End Advanced Analytics Pilot Projects

Assistant Vice President, Head of Advanced Analytics, BFS vertical April 2013 - December 2014 (1 year 9 months)

- Led the Advanced Analytics for BFS vertical managing multiple teams spread across multiple locations delivering multiple end-to-end Analytics Projects

- Helped setting up the Retention Analytics Team and Next Best Activity/ Analytics Road map for UK Based Insurance client
- Core Member of Due diligence Team for Dubai based bank
- Launched a campaign targeting strategic US banks for analytics services and Developed BFS Analytics center of Excellence offerings for new BFS Prospects

Senior Manager, Research & Analytics February 2010 - March 2013 (3 years 2 months)

- Developed the Best in class offshore Advanced Analytics Team of Highly qualified Professionals (Mostly from IIT/ISI/DSE) from scratch for US based Bank
- Managed Functional units (Modeling, E Commerce & Web Analytics, CRM, Data Analytics) for all LOB (Auto Finance, Auto Auction, Mortgage, Deposit) for US based Bank
- Performed the dual role of Building the Advanced Analytics Team and working on various innovative complex Modelling projects as an individual contributor.

GE Money

2 years 7 months

Team Lead, Risk Analytics August 2009 - January 2010 (6 months)

- Developed Acquisition strategy
- Developed Credit Index/Fraud Index using 4 different Model scores
 (Application score, FICO Score, Fraud score, ASA Score) and derived a
 Master Index for Product Assignment & Credit Limit Assignment
- Mentor for new/experienced hires for Modeling Techniques
- Initiated Statistics classes for R&A Team

Senior Analyst January 2008 - July 2009 (1 year 7 months)

- Developed Fraud Model

- Reduced 30% TNF cases with revenue loss protection in the order of \$ 1.5 $\,$ MM
- Developed Credit Limit decrease strategy
- CLD Strategy using HRT (High Risk Trigger score), Utilization and open to buy causing to lose no more than \$ 8 of good sales for \$ 1 of bad charge off avoidance.
- Developed Authorization strategy
- Manual referral Authorization strategy that helped reducing referral volumes by 40% resulting reductions in loss exposure of \$ 1MM and increased sales up to \$ 12 MM

#

Analyst

July 2007 - December 2007 (6 months)

- Developed Customer Segmentation for PowerSport Portfolio
- Solved the complexity of clustering project by improving the existing methodology and reducing the project time by at least 3 days

American Express

Business Analyst

May 2006 - June 2007 (1 year 2 months)

- Developed 20 best in class response Models using Logistic Regression for various Cross sell/Up Sell offers for international markets (Mexico, Canada, Italy, UK, Japan and Australia) reducing marketing spend by $\sim 50\%$ and capturing $\sim 90\%$ responders
- Developed Best in class BT (Balance Transfer) Models for Mexico and
 Australia for the first time which were the highlights of Executive Dashboard

Education

Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay M.Sc., Applied Statistics & Informatics · (2004 - 2006)

Hindu College, Delhi University

B.Sc., Mathematics · (2001 - 2004)